# TIJU MATHEW GEORGE

806-789-2481 • tiju.m.george@gmail.com • <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/george-tiju">http://www.linkedin.com/in/george-tiju</a> • <a href="mailto:github.com/tijugeorge">github.com/tijugeorge</a> • <a href="https://tijugeorge.github.io/">https://tijugeorge.github.io/</a> Tallahassee, Florida

### **SUMMARY**

Self-motivated, results-driven software engineer and technically sound MIS (Data Science) and CS Masters graduate interested in machine learning. Experienced in Python programming and front end technologies. Keen to learn new skills, tools and ability to adjust to demanding projects.

# **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Programming: Python, SQL, Java, R.

Front-End: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JavaScript

Databases: Microsoft SQL Server, NoSQL- MongoDB, Oracle 11g, Hadoop

OS and Tools: Windows 7/8/10, Linux (Ubuntu), Google App Engine, Jinja, MatLab, SAS EM & EG, Eclipse, Flask, Tensor Flow.

Cloud and Visualization: MS Azure, AWS, Google Cloud, Gephi, Tableau

#### **PROJECTS**

Movie Trailer Website (Python, HTML, CSS) - https://github.com/tijugeorge/Movie-trailer-website

- Server-side code written in Python to store a list of my favorite movies, including box art imagery and a movie trailer URL.
- This data is then served to a web page using HTML and CSS allowing visitors to review these movies and watch the trailers.

## Build a Portfolio (HTML, CSS, Bootstrap) - https://github.com/tijugeorge/Build-a-Portfolio

- Developed a personal portfolio page using HTML, CSS, and the Bootstrap framework.
- The page is fully responsive and works on mobile, tablet, and desktop browsers.

Multi-user Blog (Python, Google App Engine, SQL, cryptography standards like MD5, SHA2, HMAC used)-

https://multi-user-blog-163400.appspot.com/

- A multi user blog where users can sign in & post blog posts as well as 'Like' & 'Comment' on other posts made on the blog.
- Hosted this blog on Google App Engine and created an authentication system for users to be able to register and sign in and then create blog posts.

# Social Network Analysis using Facebook API (Sentiment Analysis) (Python) - https://github.com/tijugeorge/Project-2

- Used the Facebook community page for online live comments analysis for data mining.
- Sentiment analysis done on the retrieved data using the python and its Machine Learning and statistical packages.

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Software Engineer, HPE (Aspire Systems Inc.), Tallahassee, FL

Sept 2016 - Present

- Research, design and later implement codes to the testing environment and preparation of technical documentation.
- Worked on panel testing and writing queries to achieve the daily target of 2-4 change order requests.
- Investigate, identify root cause of performance by evaluating and specified solutions to systems of Florida Healthcare Medicaid interchange (UI) payments and complying with HIPAA regulations.
- Worked on test cases and deployed in model office which is a prototype of production systems and monitor the changes.

# Teaching Assistant/IT Student Analyst, Texas Tech University-IT Division, Lubbock, TX

Dec 2014- May 2016

- Served as teaching aide for class of 40 students when professor went to conferences; graded and supervise examinations.
- Worked as technical analyst for IT Division by providing front line technical support to Staff, Faculty & students with daily closure of 15-20 tickets on priority basis.
- Troubleshot computer network and communication protocols including TCP/IP, UDP & HTTP.

### Process Expert, Maersk, India

Feb 2014 - Jun 2014

- Designed and created backend data access modules using PL/SQL stored procedures and Oracle.
- Assisted software development team with various SDLC stages in agile environment & documenting technical specifications.

## **EDUCATION**

# Texas Tech University, TX - Master of Science in Management Information Systems-Data Science

May 2016

Coursework: Decision Theory and Business Analytics, Data and Text Mining, Prescriptive Analysis, Business Problem Solving, Database Concepts, Statistical Concepts, Data management and Business Intelligence

### University of Mumbai, India - Master of Science in Computer Science

May 2012

Coursework: Distributed Computing, Algorithm and Data Structures, Compiler Design, Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning, Image and Digital Signal processing, Pattern recognition, DBMS, Optimization Techniques and Embedded Systems.

# **Udacity -Full Stack Developer Nanodegree/Machine learning**

in progress

Developing a neighborhood map which consumes the Google API, Wikipedia API and Yelp reviews for understanding the neighborhood while travelling. Trained in **Naïve Bayes, SVM, Decision trees, Regressions, Outliers, Clustering, PCA** though machine learning course of Udacity

# **EXTRA-CURRICULAR & AWARDS**

- Volunteer tutor at Institutional Diversity, Equity & Community serving the Lubbock area, TX.
- Secretarial Coordinator for Big Data Symposium at Texas Tech University 2016.
- Counselor at Texas Tech University Chess Department for summer 2015.
- Awarded with Study Abroad Competitive Scholarship by Texas Tech University